Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Area X Gallery records
1977-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Area X Gallery
2.4 linear feet
The East Village Area X Gallery records measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1977-1988. The collection consists primarily of artists files for fifteen artists represented by or of interest to the gallery. The files are varied but may include biographical information, correspondence, financial and inventory records, printed materials, and photographs. Gallery records include scattered financial records, publicity files, and printed materials.
Provenance
The records of the Area X Gallery were donated by Bobbie Sioux Xuereb, the gallery's founder and director, in 1998.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
The Area X Gallery was founded in New York City by Bobbie Sioux Xuereb (Goldberg) in February 1984. Located at 200 E. 10th St., the gallery was part of the larger East Village art scene of the 1980s. Among the artists represented by gallery were Keith Achepohl, John Himmelfarb, Leon Johnson, Michael McCollum, and Louis Mueller. As with many of the East Village galleries, the Area X Gallery closed in 1987.
Scope and Content Note
The East Village Area X Gallery records measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1977-1988. The collection consists primarily of artists files for fifteen artists represented by or of interest to the gallery. The files are varied but may include biographical information, correspondence, financial and inventory records, printed materials, and photographs. Gallery records include scattered financial records, publicity files, and printed materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series:
Series 1: Artists Files, 1977-1988 (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Finacial Records, 1984-1987 (Box 2; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Publicity Files, 1980-1987 (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1980-1987 (box 3; 3 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Artists--East Village (New York, N.Y.); Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Art galleries, Commercial--East Village (New York, N.Y.); Art, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Art, Modern--20th century--East Village (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects-Geographical:
East Village (New York, N.Y.)
Types of Materials:
Financial records; Photographs
Names:
Xuereb, Bobbie Sioux
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Artists Files, 1977-1988, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
  Artists files are for artists represented by Area X Gallery artists or of interest to the gallery. Files are varied but include biographical information, correspondence with the artist and buyers, financial and consignment/inventory records with pricelists, printed materials, and photographs of works of art and some photographs of artists.
  - Achepohl, Keith (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Consignment and Inventory Forms, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aquino, Sol (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Iventory and Consignment Forms, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Invoice, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Exhibiton Announcements, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Catherine, Norman (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Inventory and Price Lists, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ernst, Eric (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lists of Works of Art, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Slides, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Negatives and Transparencies, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gerstein, Linda (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Slides and Contact Sheets, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Himmelfarb, John (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Invoices and Consignment, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Price Lists, 1984-circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Shipping Receipts, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Photographs, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Huddleston, Jarrett (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pricelists and Inventory, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Invoices, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Shipping Receipts, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Slides, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Jahoda, Susan (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Notes and Lists, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Inventory and Price Lists, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Exhibtion Announcements, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Johnson, Leon (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Notes, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Inventory and Price Lists, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Invoices, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Photographs, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Keller, Gemaine (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Slides, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lehman, Joni (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Consignment Forms, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Photographs, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Slides, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Levinthal, David (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Consignment Forms, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Invoices and Receipts, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Notes and Lists, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Articles and Clippings, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Photographs, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - McCollum, Mike (Box 1)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Lists of Works of Art, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Consignment Forms, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Clippings and Articles, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Slides, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Mueller, Louis (Box 2)
    - Biographical Information, circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Price Lists, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Notes, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Press Releases and Articles, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Transparencies, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rosin, Paul (Box 2)
    - Biographical Information, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notes, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Consignment Forms and Lists of Works of Art, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Shipping Receipts, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Clippings and Articles, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Slides and Transparencies, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Artists (Box 2)
    - Ackerman, Mickey and Alberta, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Brekke, John, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Noe, Todd E., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Pascal, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Prys, Janet, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Utterback, Walter, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Wax, Jack, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Zucca, Edward, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Artists of Interest, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Master Copies of Artist Bibliographies, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Financial Records, 1984-1987, Series 2:; (Box 2; 0.5 linear feet)
  Financial records include five ledgers regarding sales, inventory, and cash disbursements from February 1984 to 1987. Also included are copies of artists' financial statements, copies of invoices sent to buyers, tax information, and receipts from the Gallery's everyday operations.
  - Ledgers (Box 2)
    - Sales, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Sales and Inventory, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Sales, by Artist, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Cash Disbursement, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Cash Receipts, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Artists' Statements, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Invoices, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Taxes, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Gallery Receipts, 1984-1986, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 37-41)
- Publicity Files, 1980-1987, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
  Publicity files include press releases and distribution lists, contact lists for magazines, critics, and museums, and printed materials about corporate collections and collectors.
  - Contacts--Magazines, Critics, 1981-circa 1987, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Corporate Collections and Collectors, 1980-circa 1984, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Press Releases, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases--Master List for Distribution, circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, circa 1980-1987, Series 4:; (Box 3; 3 folders)
  Found are clippings and articles relating to art, art galleries, artists, and exhibits; newsletters and press releases from other galleries; and miscellaneous pamphlets.
  - Clippings and Articles, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters and Press Releases, circa 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets and Articles, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 9)